
"""This is a Te Reo Maori Quiz."""

import random
import time
import os


questions_fruit = [
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for APPLE?",
        "answers": ["Āporo", "Wharepaku",
                    "Pākihi", "Kōtirotiro"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for ORANGE?",
        "answers": ["Ārani", "Kōwhitiwhiti",
                    "Karāti", "Tīhi"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for PEACH?",
        "answers": ["Wharepēke", "Kōraka",
                    "Pītiti", "Pūteketeke"],
        "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for LEMON?",
        "answers": ["Kōremu", "Rēmana",
                    "Wharepure", "Pūtangitangi"],
        "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for WATERMELON?",
        "answers": ["Pūmate", "Wharemērēti",
                    "Kōmerenika", "Merengi"],
        "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for PLUM?",
        "answers": ["Wharepēke", "Kōraka",
                    "Paramu", "Pūteketeke"],
        "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for GRAPES?",
        "answers": ["Kerepe", "Kōraka",
                    "Pītiti", "Pūteketeke"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
]

questions_veggies = [
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for CORN?",
        "answers": ["Pukarākau", "Kānga",
                    "Whakangāka", "Pōhākai"],
        "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for ONION?",
        "answers": ["Wairuku", "Pāhukura",
                    "Whakarāhui", "Aniana"],
        "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for CABBAGE?",
        "answers": ["Kāpeti", "Pōhakuwhero",
                    "Whakamauī", "Kōhutukawa"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for CAULIFLOWER?",
        "answers": ["Kareparāoa", "Whakanuihuka",
                    "Pōhakahukarere", "Kōhurere"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for CARROT?",
        "answers": ["Whakamārama", "Pōharakoa",
                    "Kāreti", "Kōhutau"],
        "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for CUCUMBER?",
        "answers": ["Kōhuhina", "Pōhapara",
                    "Whakaninihā", "Kūkama"],
        "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for LETTUCE?",
        "answers": ["Kōhutaka", "Rētihi",
                    "Whakatakataka", "Pōharua"],
        "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for POTATO?",
        "answers": ["Rīwai", "Whakanoho",
                    "Kōhununu", "Pōharore"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
]

questions_gen_items = [
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for TV?",
        "answers": ["Pātakaarata", "Pouaka Whakaata",
                    "Whakamāharahara", "Hītoriwhakaāhua"],
        "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for COFFEE TABLE?",
        "answers": ["Rākaukawhe", "Papara Kawhe",
                    "Kōrerorangi", "Whakararaenga"],
        "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for BED?",
        "answers": ["Whakararoturuma", "Moemoeāroha",
                    "Whakapōtiki", "Moenga"],
        "correct_answer": 3
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for DRAWERS?",
        "answers": ["Whakararanga", "Pūtātara",
                    "Toroa", "Whakapātaka"],
        "correct_answer": 2
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for SMARTPHONE?",
        "answers": ["Waea Atamai", "Tamahiko",
                    "Pātikaranga", "Kōreromahi"],
        "correct_answer": 0
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for TOASTER?",
        "answers": ["Tahuwhakarihi", "Whakatōhi",
                    "Kōreropūhoro", "Pūrahatete"],
        "correct_answer": 1
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the Maori word for OVEN?",
        "answers": ["Pōkaiwhakaara", "Tīwaiwera",
                    "Whakararotu", "Umu"],
        "correct_answer": 3
    },
]

random.shuffle(questions_fruit)
random.shuffle(questions_veggies)
random.shuffle(questions_gen_items)

hard_mode_time_limit = 15


def delete_multiple_lines():
    """Clear the console output."""
    if os.name == "nt":
        os.system("cls")


def countdown(c, time_limit):
    """Countdown timer when starting quiz."""
    while c >= 0:
        if c > 0:
            print(f"{c}...", end="\r")
        else:
            print("GO!")
        time.sleep(1)
        c -= 1


def play_quiz(questions, hard_mode=False):
    """Play the quiz."""
    score = 0
    total_questions = len(questions)
    time_limit = hard_mode_time_limit if hard_mode else 0
    start_time = time.time()

    for question in questions:
        score += ask_question(question)

        if time_limit > 0 and time.time() - start_time >= time_limit:
            delete_multiple_lines()
            print("Times Up!")
            break

    if time_limit == 0 or time.time() - start_time < time_limit:
        print("Quiz finished! Your score:", score, "/", total_questions)

    while True:
        play_again = input("Would you like to play again? (Yes/No): ").lower()
        if play_again == "yes":
            delete_multiple_lines()
            return True
        elif play_again == "no":
            delete_multiple_lines()
            return False
        else:
            print("Hmm, that doesn't seem right. Only type in YES or NO.")


def quiz_start():
    """Start the quiz."""
    while True:
        print("Kia ora! Welcome to the Māori Language Quiz.")
        print("Please choose a category to test your Te Reo Māori knowledge:")
        print("1. Fruits")
        print("2. Vegetables")
        print("3. General Items")

        category_choice = input("Enter the number of your chosen category: ")

        if category_choice == "1":
            delete_multiple_lines()
            difficulty = input("""
            Choose difficulty level \n
            1. Easy (no time limit)\n
            2. Hard (15 second time limit)\n\n
            Select what difficulty you want: """).lower()
            delete_multiple_lines()
            countdown(3, hard_mode_time_limit if difficulty == "2" else 0)
            if difficulty == "2":
                play_again = play_quiz(questions_fruit, hard_mode=True)
            else:
                play_again = play_quiz(questions_fruit)
        elif category_choice == "2":
            delete_multiple_lines()
            difficulty = input("""
            Choose difficulty level \n
            1. Easy (no time limit)\n
            2. Hard (15 second time limit)\n\n
            Select what difficulty you want: """).lower()
            delete_multiple_lines()
            countdown(3, hard_mode_time_limit if difficulty == "2" else 0)
            if difficulty == "2":
                play_again = play_quiz(questions_veggies, hard_mode=True)
            else:
                play_again = play_quiz(questions_veggies)
        elif category_choice == "3":
            delete_multiple_lines()
            difficulty = input("""
            Choose difficulty level \n
            1. Easy (no time limit)\n
            2. Hard (15 second time limit)\n\n
            Select what difficulty you want: """).lower()
            delete_multiple_lines()
            countdown(3, hard_mode_time_limit if difficulty == "2" else 0)
            if difficulty == "2":
                play_again = play_quiz(questions_gen_items, hard_mode=True)
            else:
                play_again = play_quiz(questions_gen_items)
        else:
            print("That doesn't seem right.")
            continue

        if not play_again:
            break

    print("Thank you for playing the Māori Language Quiz. Ka kite anō!")


def ask_question(question):
    """Asks the questions."""
    print(question["question"])
    for i, answer in enumerate(question["answers"]):
        print(f"{i+1}. {answer}")

    valid_answers = [str(i+1) for i in range(len(question["answers"]))]

    while True:
        user_answer = input("Enter the number of your answer: ")
        if user_answer in valid_answers:
            break
        else:
            print("""
            Sorry, that's not a valid option.
            Please choose an answer from 1 to 4.\n""")

    user_answer = int(user_answer)

    if user_answer == question["correct_answer"] + 1:
        delete_multiple_lines()
        print("Correct!\n")
        return 1
    else:
        correct_index = question["correct_answer"]
        correct_answer = question["answers"][correct_index]
        delete_multiple_lines()
        print("Incorrect! The correct answer was:", correct_answer, "\n")
        return 0


quiz_start()
